this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at sc-radio.net
SC radio is brought to you by the IEEE
computer Society by IEEE software
Magazine online at computer.org software
welcome to software engineering radio
I'm your host Akshay manchale my guest
today is Ashley Peacock and we're going
to talk about diagramming and software
engineering Ashley is a staff engineer
and architect working in the UK tech
industry with over 10 years of
experience he has experience across the
tech stack with particular focus on
back-end Technologies he is an avid user
of diagrams and a huge advocate for the
power and conveying ideas documenting
architectures and whiteboarding problems
he's the author of the book creating
software with modern diagramming
techniques Ashley welcome to the show
thank you very much for having me glad
to be here to get started I want to get
a sense of why you think diagramming is
important in other forms of engineering
diagramming may be a requirement if you
are a civil engineer maybe you know
you're adding diagrams as a requirement
by law but in software it's not so much
so that it's required it's nice to have
but I know you're a huge advocate for
diagramming so why do you think it's
important and why do don't we use it
more often I think the power from a
diagram comes from the ease with which
it can make information digestible so
I'm sure you've experienced someone sent
you a document to read and you've opened
it up and it's just a huge like wall of
text and the chances are you either left
in the tab and thought I'll read that
later because you don't want to read it
or you read it and you skim reader you
don't read properly but it can just be
really hard to digest just a wall of
text or if you're a conference
there's a reason that you have slides
for a conference speaker it's because
there's something on the screen for you
to read something you can digest that's
easy for you to digest now if you talk
about software engineering documenting
your architecture or explaining
something to someone with some sort of
visual diagram that can really help them
to understand the problem
and standard architecture that kind of
stuff in the company that I work for
it's got to the point now where I could
use the word famous but like I'm
slightly famous within the company I
work for for diagramming to the point
that people find it so useful and so
much easier to understand problems and
information I would go to meetings there
wouldn't be my meetings and they would
be like oh I'm sure Ashley's got a
diagram that can explain this to us and
obviously I did not have a diagram
available to them because it wasn't my
meeting but it kind of shows the point
of they weren't necessarily used to
diagrams but once they saw the power in
them they were kind of they were much
more open to them and another example my
CTO at the time he kind of showered out
one of the diagrams I used because he
wanted people to use diagrams he'd seen
the power of diagrams and I'd create a
rather large system design kind of
architecture document and it really kind
of pushed my career forward because I
was able to express myself through
diagrams my ideas my proposals and I can
make them digestible for anyone that
want to read those documents yeah you
make a great point that it's good for
communicating ideas and I think it makes
it easier for the readers from a writer
perspective at what points do you use
diagrams in general software engineering
life cycles
so I split diagrams into two types of
diagram I call them kind of short-lived
diagrams that are more ad hoc and
long-lived diagrams that you want to
typically commit along with your source
code so the short-lived ones are used
during a brainstorming session or do
repairing to help explain something to
someone so if if we're pairing together
and I'm trying to explain to you the
problem we're trying to solve or
a piece of code for example I can just
quickly whip up a diagram to help
explain that if you're not quite
understanding what I'm saying with my
words I can try with a visual approach
instead it's not always required it's
more it's something you can reach for
like an extra tool than your your tool
set that you can help explain things to
others easily and the long left side is
the stuff you put along with your source
code in your repository and that will be
things like your architecture so anyone
who wants to understand about a given
systems architecture there should be a
place they can go they can read that
document and understand at a glance
rather than reading a huge wall of text
or relying on asking someone who's got
information in their brain they can just
go read it that's a really common one I
want to get a sense of why you think
people don't use it more often there's a
clear usefulness to it when you are the
reader when you're the consumer for any
sort of software architecture that's
represented in a diagram makes it
simpler easier to understand but we
don't really use it as often so what's
the friction here I think there's a few
different factors that go into this one
I think some of it is there are older
Technologies or older standards one them
being
uml which stands for the unified
modeling language it was kind of praised
in the 90s as a way to standardize
creating software diagrams and I think
it's kind of got a bad reputation they
made some maybe Choice decisions I think
they tried to make it almost too
standard and or too restrictive they
want things done in a certain way rather
than
focusing on the power the diagram could
bring they focused on the notation for
example which is not so important so I
think people have got used to hearing
from someone oh you're not old it's not
good anymore or they've had someone's
had a bad experience with it and it kind
of almost like Chinese Whispers of this
thing is not valuable because someone
they've heard someone who doesn't like
this thing
and the other thing is in recent years
there's been lots of developments in the
tooling for crank diagrams so maybe 10
years ago you would have had to manually
draw this diagram using boxes and lines
and it would take you ages and if
someone was to ask you to change that
diagram after you've drawn 15 boxes and
they want to add two boxes in the middle
it's going to take you half an hour to
redraw all your boxes so
if you'd gone for that experience it's
quite painful I used to do that and if
someone would request changes to my
diagram a little part of me inside would
cry because I knew that it was going to
take me hours to redraw this diagram I
guess the other one is is education
maybe people aren't aware of it or they
don't have to get started with it if
there's not that many people that are
doing it and I think it's got some
popularity but it's not widespread it
can be hard to know who to speak to to
get a better understanding of
diagramming where to get started the
types of diagram that kind of stuff yeah
the uml model is definitely something
that comes to mind when you talk about
diagrams and maybe it's a little too
popular for its own good in the past
with the traditional software
development Cycles
do you think that the uml diagram was in
itself reviewed is that something that
had to conform to standards and was that
just for standard sake or was it
something that they could take and
convert to code or convert to something
was there any particular reason that you
see why there was so much rigidity in
the uml style diagrams so I think with
any
standard the whole point is it it is
standard so you see a class diagram for
example that represents classes in your
code base that you create and if I
create one of microbase and you put them
side by side the class names will be
different because they're different
classes but the actual structure of them
and the way the lines are drawn and so
on those are
standard in their model and to a point
that makes sense because if you didn't
have
a blueprint of what to go from there
wouldn't be so much value because it's
people wouldn't know what to do right
like all the diagrams would just it'll
be their own flavor of diagram so that's
standard but they went very heavy on the
kind of notation and I don't think they
focus so much on the kind of use cases
which I think for me I care less about
what type of diagram someone uses and
more about the information and the use
case they're trying to convey kind of
classic example is the other day I was I
work with some a colleague
and he was modeling classes
if you were to follow the letter he
would have drawn a class diagram but he
drew what's called an entity
relationship diagram which is used more
for database schemas but all he cared
about was the names and how they related
to each other he didn't care about
methods or Properties or in the case of
a database The Columns he just cared
about the relationships so for that use
case it didn't matter which one he used
so there was no real point in ruining
that like hard work that he'd put in you
can obviously point out that you know
maybe you in future but for him he got
out of it what he needed and the type of
diagram was kind of less important and
the use case was and the information was
the important bit I think that's what
got lost a little bit yeah that makes
sense in the diagramming world there's
uml with its fragility other modern
diagramming types that you are an
advocate for or you see people using is
there are there names associated with it
for specific types of ideas that you
want to convey so this DML diagrams that
we've talked about a little bit and
there's from you are now there's 12
maybe 15 diagram types in total I
generally use two or three tops
because I think most common use cases
can be covered by maybe four types of
diagram and that'll cover like 95 of
your use cases the two from uml one we
talked about briefly which is class
diagrams so those are used for
understanding classes and their
dependencies so you could draw Class A B
and C you could show how they one
depends on the other and you can show
all the methods and properties on each
class and
you can use those by using the two ways
I would say one it's just understanding
so I'm sure we've all been in there with
we're working on the same monolith and
you're trying to code change and you're
in a bit of code that you've not worked
on before and you go into your IDE you
find this to say the controller because
it's like a you know HTTP request and
you're clicking through the files and
before you know you've got like 10 tabs
open in your IDE and you're trying to
remember you know which class talks to
which class and all the dependencies
and sometimes it's easier to step back
and just extract that information rather
than trying to keep it in your head and
just draw it out especially if you're
pairing you then have the same
understanding and you can draw that
diagram together you can validate that
it it makes sense and then if you want
to you can go one step further and once
you've drawn that diagram if you're
making a code change that is not small
you know if you're doing I don't know
change some text or changing tiny
Behavior I wouldn't do this but if
you're doing a larger refactor you can
perhaps draw the class diagram as you'd
like it to be when you're finished
you're a factor and you can almost
prototype using the diagrams and see if
that makes sense because it's a lot
cheaper than doing the refactor and then
realizing oh I've now got like a
circular dependency or something because
you haven't thought ahead so it's about
planning and understanding your class
diagrams the second one from uml is
sequence diagrams and these at least I
would say this is my favorite diagram if
I have to pick a favorite because I
think it's just it's so versatile for so
many use cases there are two things I
visually lies with it one of them are
like user flows so
understanding how a user uses your
system
so if you have
a login flow or a sign up flow if you're
in a you know let's say a microservice
architecture you need to understand the
steps that that user is going to take
and which systems it's going to touch so
they're going to fill out the form click
a button something's going to happen and
you can understand
either a how that currently works if it
already exists or B if you're thinking
about architecture you can draw the use
cases of how the system users are going
to use your system so that you make sure
you build the architecture the fits or
your users are actually going to do and
the second one is for code flows so you
can have
steps in the sequence that are for
classes sending messages
to other classes and again that's an
understanding thing I wouldn't use a
design but if you're looking at the
example we talked about earlier in the
monolith you could also use
a sequence diagram to understand the
messages being passed from cast class
because obviously the class diagram
gives you the dependency graph but
that's very different to the order of
execution in the sequence diagram
yeah that's a common thing when you're
reading through code you're trying to
build this mental model of a calls b b
calls C and then you have some State
that's in C that gets passed on to Z so
if I'm hearing you write secret diagrams
are one way to represent that in a more
concise and easy to understand way is
there anything else to it around
sequence diagrams that you think AIDS
understanding the only other ones maybe
are you can also model almost like happy
and sad parts in your system so we
talked a little bit about use cases and
how people use your system you can do
the same for code as well that are happy
and sad pass so you can kind of think
about all the possible ways people could
interact with your system and then how
it responds and similarly that can be
useful for when it comes to doing
testing for example so it can be really
easy to
dive in code feature and then you you
need to test it works right so you might
write immuno tests but also quite
commonly you might do some manual
testing or depending where you work you
might actually have like a test engineer
that does that for you if you've drawn
out these happy and sad paths you can
use that in that kind of conversation
about look this is how the we think it's
going to be used and the test engineer
might think of more scenarios but the
very least they're going to appreciate
that you've put some thought into
testing and you've got something for
them to kind of start with rather than
having to work it all out I know talking
about diagrams in an audio only format
is a little bit challenging and in the
book you use an example company or an
example service to Aid understanding
throughout the book in various chapters
so I think you talk about streamy as a
service can you just give an overview
maybe of that and then we'll use that as
an example going forward in some of the
more detailed descriptions of
diagramming techniques and tools Etc
so streamy is a video streaming company
you can think of it like a Netflix
and they're kind of just getting started
as a company they're you know they're
not three engineers in the garage but
let's just say that 20 Engineers for
example so they're just getting going
they've got some funding and they are
going to build the next big video stream
platform
and to do that we're going to go through
the Journey that streamy would go
through in order to build I guess their
MVP so that the minimum viable product
the smallest thing they can build but
the the different steps of how I would
approach that kind of Greenfield brand
new project and the diagrams I would use
to help build the architecture that
streaming needs okay awesome so starting
with that let's talk a little bit about
more modern diagramming techniques so
you're in that room how do you get
started like do you start with a diagram
maybe you're collaborating on a
whiteboard
how do you make use of these diagrams to
convey ideas and come up with that
architecture for this next Generation
streamy streaming platform can you talk
a little bit about that yeah so I'll
give a quick overview of the different
tools that are available there's quite a
few before
modern diagram and came along there were
well everyone would have used a UI tool
so something like Microsoft physio for
example that you have to pay for there
are open source Alternatives like
diagrams.net or Droid iOS they're
probably the one that everyone knows
it's free it's open source it's all in
your browser it looks very pretty you
basically drag and drop everything
around on their kind of interface but
it's very it's very slow as we talked
about earlier if something if you know
you need to update that diagram or
change that diagram it can be very time
consuming and it's a maintenance
nightmare there are other problems with
it it will save in an unreadable format
for a human so if you ever use draw.io
and if you went and looked at the save
file it's a huge blob of like XML from
memory you have no idea what's going on
because it's written for a machine which
means you can't diff it and you could
commit it to your
project if you want to but the next time
someone comes to edit that diagram
they're going to load into their Google
Cloud they're going to change the
diagram and they're probably going to
forget to update it so now you've got a
mismatch between what's committed in
your repository it's sound your Google
cloud on my Google Cloud they're all out
of sync it's a bit of a nightmare and if
you want to put let's say an
architecture diagram in your Ruby you
need to export the image out of that
program and store that in the repository
which now means your source of truth is
disconnected from the kind of final
artifact that you want people to read
classic example is someone leaves the
company and that diagram for your
architecture is in their Google Drive
and at all companies but where I work
there's a choice when someone leaves of
whether you keep a Google cloud and it's
given to someone else or you just delete
it forever and once it's deleted it's
gone you'll never get it back so if
that's your architecture
or your documentation for your
architecture and that person leaves your
documentation is now effectively gone
and someone's have to redraw that
diagram so as you can probably tell I'm
not a huge fan of the manual tools they
have lasers if you're drawing a very
complex diagram or let's say you're
presenting to Executives and it needs to
look really really pretty
then sure draw it in there as a one-off
but generally speaking for the diagrams
I'm mainly you can talk about about
building software architecture I would
stay away from those the tool that I
think started the movement towards more
automated tools
and the movement or the practice is kind
of called diagrams as code is plan your
map and that's a tool around Java I
think it was around the 2009ish I think
it came out and it basically allowed you
to write markup that's similar to
markdown so you might have a and then
like a hyphen and an arrow to B and then
you can put like a label on it with a
code or something and give it a label
for that line and it would draw you a
box of a to B with an arrow and it will
just render that for you so you'd have
to draw anything and it's super simple
to use problem with it though
is that it's because of Reddit Java you
can't run that anywhere you have to run
you know the Java server you can
obviously run it on your your Mac or
your PC or whatever but it's it's a bit
of a nightmare to kind of get set up
with so it has plugins that you can
enhance its capabilities with so out of
the box it offers you the uml diagrams I
talked about plus all the ones that we
haven't touched on
and you can enhance it with other types
of diagrams that have come around since
but the new kid on the Block
is mermaid and the book focuses on
mermaid and is written in JavaScript
which is the main difference the markup
is remarkably similar if you looked at
the plant uml and dynamic syntax
for the most part they're pretty
identical because there's only so much
kind of innovation you can have in
drawing these types of diagram because
they are mostly uml diagrams so there
are standards associated with them
because it's written JavaScript that
means it runs in the browser and because
you can run the browser that means it's
been widely adopted which is the big big
center point I think plan uml is awesome
mermaid's also awesome but mermaid the
big one for me
is the adoption so if you're using your
Fusion jira Confluence notion if you're
using the big one GitHub you can put
your mermaid markup in a markdown file
on GitHub and with no work whatsoever
when someone's used that markdown file
in their browser GitHub will render that
diagram for you so that means your
source for your diagram is compared in
your project
and once updated they can just go in
edit the markdown commit it and it's
updated so your single Source Truth for
let's say your architecture
is now in your project it's stored
there's no going out of sync and the
rendering is just done for you
and if you had external knowledge
centers for example let's say you export
that content and you host your own
knowledge site for example that's easy
to do in the build right you could just
use the tooling that Nana gives you it
has a command interface and you can just
render those those diagrams in the
markdown file
before you render those HDR Pages for
example is it and you get all of the
versioning for free it sounds like
because I was wondering how do you do
versioning and diagrams and how do you
keep track of older versions maybe so I
guess this gives you a very nice way to
just version in inside of your
repository itself yeah exactly you can
basically just rely on me the kind of
the version controls everyone's got used
to these days double version of diagrams
you can look at the old versions you
can't lose this diagram it's well
and let's get help was to you know erase
all the hard drives and whatnot then we
hope that doesn't happen but you know
that diagram's not going anywhere nice
can we take something from the streamy
service some flow some interaction and
kind of describe what this mermaid or
plant your mail syntax kind of looks
like in order to visualize that how hard
is it how easy is it can you shed some
light come back yep I can do that and
I'm going to start where I would
logically start if I was streaming and I
was doing this in the real world and I'd
been given this Greenfield project to do
and that's understanding the domain that
streamy is working in for that I would
lean on domain driven design and create
a domain model that we can do using
mermaid for listeners we have a full
episode on domain driven design and I'll
leave a link to that
in the description so the way I approach
domain driven design and I would listen
to the episode for more detail because
I'm not going to be able to cover it in
this in this space but I would think
about the main entities that I working
extremely care about so the things we
talk about when we're in meetings that
the customers interact with what are
those and we need to get those down and
we need to get the names agreed
it's one of the main kind of tenets of
domain driven design is that everyone
speaks the same language so if we're
talking about let's say a title if you
go onto a video stream website you watch
titles something might call them videos
it doesn't really matter what you call
them there's no right and wrong what you
call something as long as it fits your
domain there are obviously some ways to
do it wrong if you call it a desk it's
probably very confusing but as long as
you give it a sensible name that's fine
and your models also might look
different if you've got two sets of
people and they both modeled
streamy they probably come up with
completely different things so in your
head now you might be thinking about
what stream looks like it probably looks
very different
I'm going to describe so we have our
title we're going to use a class diagram
for this because I think it's the most
appropriate diagram to represent the
domain model
although they're not there's no
properties there's no methods it's just
a domain model they're just names but
it's the closest thing in diagrams that
represent a domain model because when we
convert this domain model into code all
these entities should exist as classes
in our code base so we have our title
that'll be a box and connected so with
arrows going to this title you might
have different types in uml we call this
generalization in programming you think
of it like interface or inheritance and
you have types of TV show or short or
fill and those are types of title so
your extending title if you like and
from title a title might have seasons
and episodes for example but where
domain modeling and uml can help us
is you need to understand how many of
one thing relate to another thing so a
title for example if it was a TV show it
might have one season he might have two
seasons so on if it's a film they'll
have zero Seasons because it's it's a
film and therefore in the diagram
you have things called multiplicity and
what this effectively does is tells you
how many of one thing relates to another
thing so in the case of title and season
you can say a title has zero too many
seasons
and the season belongs to just one title
because you know season one of Game of
Thrones can obviously only relate to
Game of Thrones it can't relate to I
don't know Dexter or something it
doesn't make any sense and how do you
use this in mermaid syntax or platinum
syntax to represent so when they're made
each diagram has a type so the first
line in any mermaid is the type of
diagram so our case is a class diagram a
sequence if you seek the diagram so
forth and four a class diagram is
probably the simplest of syntax and
markup that you can probably have of any
diagram because there's no methods and
no properties we just have the names and
how they relate to each other so it's
super super simple so first line class
diagram and then let's say we want to
describe the relationship between a
title and its Seasons you would put the
word title and then you would put SSA
two hyphens and then another space and
season and then if it was to render it
you would just get title and you get
season with the line between it and
that's as simple as it possibly could be
and if you didn't want to add in and
enrich with the multiplicity either side
of those two hyphens you would just put
the multiplicities in speech marks so
one and zero to many for example and
memory would take that and it would just
rent this box in these lines it's
interesting how this renders things from
text because sometimes when I'm creating
it with UI tools I'm kind of confused
about how big certain boxes should be
should my line be bold should be really
thin does it look okay does mommy take
care of that with like default settings
and is there a way for you to change
that maybe to make it visually more
aligned to maybe your taste or the way
that you want something to stand up
yeah suddenly depending on the
environment you're in you have different
levels of control
so out the box Mermaid has its own
rendering engine so it will render
everything in its default way and it'll
look nice but if you wanted to change
certain things you can do that so
there's a type in memory called a
flowchart and it's more like
you know if you ever seen flowchart you
have circles and diamonds and it could
be like you know decisions and things
but it's their kind of generic capsule
for maybe things that don't fit into
Ross and in that example you can change
the direction for example rather than
being top to bottom it could be left to
right in the case of class diagrams
and most other types of diagrams you can
use CSS styling to change how things
look limitedly and if you're using
online Mermaid has a live editor that I
use a lot that lets you quickly create
the diagrams and it gives you kind of
two panes the left you put your memory
mark up and the right ear will just
automatically refresh every time you
change
so on that one you can do these kind of
simple things if you were rendering them
on your own website you can do whatever
you want because they're a JavaScript
kind of hooks for you to use you can
inject your own styling but even with
the kind of default and minimal more
lockdown version of mermaid you can
still change you know the colors the
borders all that kind of stuff so you
can kind of make it
branded to your company if you want to
ah and mermaid also comes with with
themes out of the box so it has a
default kind of all the boxes will be
purple for example but there are things
that make it blue or black or you know
dark mode that Everyone likes these days
that kind of stuff so it's quite
versatile and because it's open source
new things are always being added I
think yeah a balloon release comes out a
couple of weeks with new features and
new things you can do
yeah it's really powerful I think this
is very similar to what markdown does
where you have the syntax and you have
the extended markdown syntax and then
depending on the rendering engine you
might even have other syntax types like
I know
different branding engines have
different ways to render code blocks
that I like some of them have syntax
highlightings and they don't so this is
somewhat akin to that and I guess what
you're saying is that you can also
override it similar to how you can with
a markdown rendering engine that's very
cool can you draw sequence diagrams that
you mentioned earlier is it possible to
use mermaid for something like sequence
diagrams or maybe even just uml itself
or is it just no uml but we'll take some
Concepts you know you have the boxes and
the lines without all of the rigidity is
that the idea or can you also get all of
you know your model sequence diagrams
and just plain simpler representation of
diagrams yeah so I think you can do both
depending on what you're trying to do so
if you are trying to build
go on status sequence I would always
just use the sequence diagram because
it's going to handle the layout and the
rendering for you so in a sequence
diagram you have what are called
lifelines and those are the individual
nodes the messages are passing between
so let's say you had a flow for a user
being able to sign up to streaming and
create their account so they can view
titles you might have a little stick
figure so a mermaid you have what called
actors and participants and that all
that means really is it changes the
little kind of icon from a box which
represents normally like a system or
something or a class and a stick figure
which reference a person so you might
have the browser
and you have a line from the browser to
the sign up service that is retrieving
the HTML for the signup page and then
you'd have a dotted Lineback because in
sequence diagrams commonly you have a
dotted line to show responses and a
solid line to show requests so you can
easily differentiate between the two and
that will return some HTML to the
browser and that's kind of like the
first interaction in the sequence
diagram
now the user is going to submit that
to submit their details to the Sam
service which will be a post request so
on the lines going between you can put
very simple kind of notationer to
explain what's going on in these
interactions you definitely don't want
to be putting you know your Json
payloads in there these need to be like
nice and high level you know it's post
Quest and it's hitting at the same point
that's simple then when it gets to the
signup service in my you know you might
want to call out some of the stuff it
does so let's say you're working with
microservices you have your site service
and let's say you have a user service
that stores your user data
the sign up service might make a post
request to the user service so that you
have another line to another kind of
lifeline and that might return a 201 to
the site service and then that might
return a 301 to redirect the login page
to the browser so then you have a series
of interactions between different
participants and one of the really nice
things you can do in mermaid is you can
add numbers which sounds not that
powerful but if we're talking about
a sequence that has the one I described
for example in the book has 9 10
different interactions on it rather than
someone trying to describe a hole at
this point they can just say a number
six
what's happening here can you explain
this I don't understand this
it's really quite a powerful tool just
to Aid General collaboration for example
make it easier to collaborate as for
diagrams outside of uml mermaid has a
kind of capsule that I mentioned earlier
called flowcharts and those are kind of
super versatile not uml just general
flow charts where
you can draw pretty much whatever you
like and you can change the shapes of
the boxes so you can have you know
square boxes if you're doing a service
if it's you need to represent a database
you can have like the little cylinder
that's commonly used on diagrams for a
database if you're maybe drawing
a almost like a business rule companies
to work at it was a loan company so they
gave loans to people there was a
decision Engine with hundreds of rules
and each rule could be defined as a
flowchart which is you take a data point
you might have a little an arrow to a
diamond that says you know if this data
point is greater than this then go on
this path if it's less than this get on
this path and it's a really nice way of
using a simple flowchart just to
visualize business rules if you were
building this decision engine it's got
hundreds of rules as an engineer you can
just go and look
at the flowchart for the rule that
you're currently coding and it's all
there for you all the use cases or the
business objects and that flowchart one
of the other ones that I don't think
we've touched on yet is if you want to
document your architecture I always
reach for something called the C4 model
yeah let's dig into the C4 can you
describe what that is and then we'll
come back to the mermaid how to
represent that so the C4 model is a way
to model your software architecture it
was created by a guy called Simon Brown
you may have seen him speak if you go to
confident things he's quite kind of
common on the calendar of conferences
he's probably been to one you've been to
and you can use a design document model
your architecture and it's one of those
long live diagrams that I in every
system that I work on it will have a C4
model in it and what it does is it takes
what I call a focus system so the system
that you are responsible for as a team
and it helps you
document understand the architecture for
the system so in the middle you'll have
your system that you own typically above
it you have the dependents and these can
be systems or people and below it you'll
have the dependencies so any Downstream
systems that you use within C4 the name
comes from four diagrams so C4 four
diagrams and they will mostly become a c
the first one which is the one I just
described is the system context diagram
and that is the kind of 50 000 foot view
of your system and it just does it's
completely non-technical there's no
protocols there's no databases it's
purely describing almost like
the business interactions between the
different
systems so in the case of streamy you
might have a premium member for example
and you might have let's say a service
because we're going to build
microservices for example there's the
listing service and that listing service
contains all the data and all the
information for all of the titles that
streaming offers so any thing in your
architecture that wants to get
information about a title it reached out
to the listing service but obviously the
person the customer also kind of
interacts with this right because
they're going to want to view the titles
so maybe as a front-end component that
renders the titles to the user now that
listing servers to do its job
might break down and call other systems
let's say for example reviews let's say
your view titles maybe you want to store
your views separately for some reason in
a review service or you want to search
the titles and because
searching is very kind of bespoke let's
just say you want to use elasticsearch
you might have a search service right
that's completely separate for searching
the titles for example now you can draw
that on your C4 like I just described
and you can I've shown this to you know
product managers stakeholders completely
non-technical people and they're able to
digest understand what it is that you're
building and that can be that can be
really useful to help explain what
you're doing and you know the classic
question of why did this take so long or
why is this taking so long you can kind
of explain to them why you're building
it this way from a completely
non-technical view I won't go through
all of the layers of the C4 model
because I actually mainly focus on the
first two and the second one is what we
call the container View and this is then
going into the technical layer so you
have your system context for the high
level View and then if you want to zoom
in so Engineers typically will want a
bit more information than just a box
that says this is the service they might
want to know how this service is put
together what containers it has so let's
say in the listing service you can
almost think about on the first diagram
double clicking the listing service and
it zooms in and it kind of splits out
all the single Deployable units
that make up your service so when you
push the master
it deploys
what do you need to run let's say as
part of the service
you have a mobile application and also
you have a web application so you can
access your listing service Via Mobile
fire web and for whatever reason you
deploy those together from the same
repository and maybe because calls to
the get titles is expensive maybe you
have it in memory cache or something
where you hold these titles in in redis
for example and these would be three
separate containers almost in like a
boundary of your system that you could
document
and you still have your Downstream
Services that's still cool but it's just
you can almost imagine in the middle you
have like a a box with dashed lines
around that show the boundary of your
system
and anything in that boundary belongs to
this service and you can dig into it
further and further and further and as
you go through the model it digs further
and further but I've never really needed
the next two which briefly are
components and code with components
being
the high level modules that make up
each container
and one level deeper is the classes in
those components or modules but
those even if you hear Simon speak he
will generally say those are there to
enable the ability to do it but
generally the first two are all most
people need especially if you're
building microservices I would say
components maybe if you're a monolith
because it better represents your
architecture you may be able to
represent different modules within a
model that has a container perhaps is
there any difference between the
container and component in terms of the
representation because once you zoom in
one level deep is it just boxes that
encapsulate you know what it's doing
describes it and then have connectors to
other similar containers or components
so if I was doing the C4 model and I was
working in a Model F what you'd
basically have on the system context is
you probably have a stick figure or
whatever other human
and they are you know doing all of their
interactions with the monolith whatever
they're doing in the case of streamy
they're viewing titles they're reviewing
titles they're searching titles you know
updating their account they're doing
everything you would probably have to
find a general way of describing this
because you can't list everything
they're doing otherwise there's this
line is going to be it's going to be a
long line but then if you you know like
I said again I think like double
clicking zooming in on
Diamond lift and you would look at the
container
you would perhaps maybe have a single
web app
and maybe it's got a database hanging
off it
but I don't think it fairly or
accurately represents your architecture
if it is a monolith just to have that
one container because you might think
this architecture is super simple
they've got a web app and they've got a
database but when you look at that
monolith if it's
you know a 10 year old monolith and
depending how that monolith is range
because it might be the classic big ball
of mud it's not arranged at any logical
way then you're probably in terms of
diagramming I don't think you're going
to be able to do it to be honest I don't
think mostly because it's going to
change too much
because it's the monolith and second of
all they might not even be clear
components it might just be all over the
place but the likes of Shopify are
pushing and promoting modular monoliths
where or Majestic model is depending
which one you prefer where within a
single monolith you have separate
segments they kept different names for
them in in rails which what they use is
Ruby and rails they're they're often
engines and those are akin to module so
they're
self-contained segments of the code base
within the monolith so you might have
a payment module you might have a title
module for viewing the titles and
managing the data for the titles you
might have a user module for example and
if you have that monolith and that nice
structure I think you can make a
component diagram that shows up the high
level components that make up your
monolith and that's akin to you know
each
module if you were in microservices
would probably be each module would
probably be a microservice
so I think using the component diagram
for a monolith gives you a fair
representation of your architecture
versus if you are a microservices the
container level it's just enough detail
because when you zoom in assuming you're
doing microservices nicely sized
Services correctly all of the code in
there should be kind of described by
your service and the kind of underlying
components probably aren't too important
at least to have in your readme makes
sense going back to Mermaid as a tool
for representation how do you do C4 with
mermaid does it give you that visual
aspect of zooming into a particular box
that expands into a more detailed
representation is it that way or is it
just different diagrams that would be
nice I have a feeling you could possibly
if you had your own website where you
were deploying these two I go internal
knowledge base you could probably write
some JavaScript that allowed you when
you clicked on it it maybe you know
changed the image or something fancy or
scroll to another point of the page but
if you're using GitHub because actually
girls do all the work for me really I
would just have you know an architecture
markdown document and at the top I would
you know write a brief introduction of
high level view of the architecture and
what it does because I think diagrams on
their own super powerful but some words
are also you know to supplement are also
helpful and I would have the system
context diagram I would put a link to
the C4 model so if you want to read what
the C4 model is I'd put a link to the C4
model there's a website for it it's very
good and then below that I would put the
container diagram so they're both one
below the other and people can just both
view both together I think you'll be
really cool if it did what you said and
you could zoom in them but yeah man it
hasn't quite got it yet maybe we will as
for creating them in mermaid I create
them personally in flowcharts they're
really easy to make because they're
quite simple diagrams for the container
diagram when you're making the kind of
boundary of your system within flowchart
you'd have sub graphs which are like
diagrams within diagrams almost and
using that you can then make your nice
little box for your service and then
anything inside the box is what you
deploy as part of your service Mermaid
has experimental support for the C4
model I believe at the moment it only
does the system context I don't think it
does all of them yet they're looking to
add it and it uses the same syntax the
plant uml plugin for C4 users so they've
just imported it I'm not a huge fan of
the syntax I think it's quite ugly so I
don't really enjoy working with it I
think it's a bit too verbose so I'm
going to stick with the flow charts now
at least until maybe mermaid picks their
own Syntax for it because it's still
experimental so we'll see where that
goes but for now use the flowcharts and
it works it works super well
I want to switch gears a little bit into
more informal diagramming techniques
maybe just whiteboarding do you have any
particular approach that you take
towards whiteboarding and diagrams as
you would with respect to something that
you're building on a PC putting that
into a document I think the main one the
poppy one at the moment is a tool called
Mirror that's what I use generally for
any kind of whiteboarding most recently
I did a session on event storming which
is probably maybe going to be covered in
your DD talk I don't know if they're
going to talk about event storming but
it comes from
domain driven design and before for
covert and for everyone or not everyone
but for remote working was everywhere so
when people were in offices event
storming would be done with sticky notes
so and I'll explain too much about what
event storming is because it will be
here for a long time but
it's a way of understanding the kind of
key events that happen in your domain
and you would
each have stickies and you would round
your sticky you stick it on a whiteboard
and you'd basically have by the end of
the first kind of section of event
storming you would have a big line
there's a chronological line of all the
events that happen in the system
obviously in a remote world that doesn't
really work I've seen it where people
have kind of put the camera and the
people in the room have put the stickies
up and then the remote people will talk
to the people in the room about you know
hey can put this sticky here and it's a
nightmare so most recently I did it on
Miro which it's basically just an online
whiteboard you can draw all sorts of
things in Miro but because it's visual
it's it's not obviously suitable for the
diagrams we've talked about with adding
them into GitHub and so forth but for
collaboration and brainstorming and
coming together and collaborating on
something like event storming I think
Miro is probably the best tour now and
you can you can see what people's curses
are you can see what people are editing
it's quite powerful nice and with the
spectacle generation I want to see if
there are tools and techniques to
generate code or some artifact starting
with diagrams I think in the ux world
people use wireframing tools where you
draw something on a tool maybe and you
might get a static website or a static
page that represents it so are there
techniques like that for generating
maybe components modules for a service
maybe it's a monolith or something and
then you know you can draw out something
in mermaid or some other tool that
generates the required stubs for what
you're trying to build
I think we're not quite there yet for
most things like that so there's the
reverse so if you're working a
statically typed language a really
common thing you can do in let's say
Java or c-sharp is you can export a
class diagram
from your code base if you're working in
monolith you're probably not going to be
able to export it because you're
probably not going to have enough memory
but you can export segments of it
perhaps and it will generate your class
diagram not a mermaid or anything it
will just give you an image typically so
I think that's been around for quite a
while I think the one that is probably I
don't know if you can do it here maybe
you can but there's a diagram called an
entity relationship diagram that we
talked about earlier which helps you
represent
database schemas and on an entity
relationship diagram or an ERD for short
you have the tables how the tables kind
of relate to each other and the kind of
columns keys and so on so if you were
designing let's say Streamys underlying
you know data which should often be very
different to your kind of code classes
you might want to do some upfront design
with
any ID so that everyone understands the
kind of the database and you can
visualize it and make sure all the data
is you know if you want to normalize it
for example you could see if there was
any duplication or anything you could
improve it's easy to get feedback on the
design of that database from you know
maybe an architect or whoever you know
you can get some feedback on on the
diagram before you build it you know
once you've deployed it and you've got
data running through it's really hard
potentially to then go back and change
that and it's also a huge waste of time
but because the way you write your IDs I
could easily see them
once you've agreed a design
converting that into SQL because the way
you write your IDs is very close to the
SQL definitions of when you actually
create them in in your code so I can see
that one definitely being a thing if
it's not really a thing I don't know if
it is here there are tools out there the
other cool one I heard about recently
and I'm not sure how how long it's been
around but in AWS you can I think it's
called cloud formation designer or
something along those lines and you can
basically draw
diagrams in aws's console using the
product so you could draw an ec2
instance an S3 bucket and a postgres
database whatever you want and the
diagrams and it will generate you the
cloud formation for that architecture so
you could collaboratively design or
design convert your C4 model into
infrastructure's code if you're using
cloud formation or terraform obviously
in this case it's AWS so they're going
to give you cloud formation but you
could draw them in that console and it
would give you the code the underlying
cloud formation that you could then just
put straight into your
deployment Pipeline and deploy it so
that's another example of turning a
diagram into code I think that's
probably the area where diagrams has
some area of innovation I guess yeah
going in the reverse order is maybe the
last thing I want to cover starting with
a complicated piece of software a code
base maybe I join a new company and
there is this massive code base that I
want to get familiar with starting with
the diagram would be great but more
often than not they don't necessarily
have a diagram or maybe it might be
steel so starting from the code is that
a good way to generate some sort of a
diagram are there any tools to learn and
onboard into a new project or a code
base so I think the ones we've talked
about already assuming
you can commit them and the you know
when we talk about GitHub automatically
rendering mermaid diagrams in markdown
the two key ones for me that I have any
pository is the domain model I think if
you don't understand the problem space
you're working in you're probably going
to hit some problems and you can put
that you know in your readme or it could
be in a markdown off you'll read me and
the C4 model is the second one I would
always have any new Joiner that joins
you can just point them to those
resources and you can enrich the diagram
with some you know with words it's not
like you know I'm against words
definitely put some words down alongside
your diagrams but that's a really good
way for them to get up to speed with
your problem space you're working in and
the architecture
code is a trickier one because it really
is going to depend
on monoliths versus microservices versus
kind of where I am where I work at the
moment which is kind of it's the classic
of everyone hate monoliths they went to
very far on microservices and then they
realized ah this has got some other
problems so you know we're kind of
working our way back to somewhere in the
middle people like to call them like
macro services or whatever you want to
call them so commonly I might have like
a component diagram for example from the
super model that lists the high level
modules for that kind of
medium-sized service for example and
then at least they understand the high
level modules of how that code is
arranged the the trickiest thing with
code is documenting it is I wouldn't do
it too much
because it's so fluid and so easy to
change like you could draw the diagram
and it could be out date the next week
if someone you know comes in and
rehashes everything or even just
reactors a part of it refactor sorry and
there's nothing worse than out of date
documentation that I guess worse than
having no documentation at all almost
because they've gone and read the
documentation they've spent some time
reading it and then they're going to
look at the edge you know they've
checked out the code cloned it and it's
completely different and they've just
wasted loads of time reading this
document that wasn't useful so for code
itself I would be cautious about
documenting it which is why also I
talked about short-lived versus
long-lived where the Long Live diagrams
the architecture the domain model those
I commit because they've all changed
they are living documents they should be
updated but they don't update you know
how often do you change significantly
change
your domain model or your architecture
it might be once quarter or once a month
but it's not going to be so much it
becomes a burden or a Time sink versus
the short-lived which is class diagrams
or sequence diagrams they're used to
understand something in that moment but
they're probably rapidly going to become
out of date I think the only overlap or
the one that's applicable in both is
perhaps sequence diagrams if I was doing
let's say an architecture decision
record which is a document you can write
to rationalize why you're making an
architecture decision I think putting a
high level sequence diagram of the flow
that you're building for this
architecture super useful and it's
probably unlikely to change again so
that's the one that does both but yeah
integrated ways and I think with that
we'll end the show actually thank you so
much for coming and talking about
diagramming and some of the tools to
really build your diagrams and make it
easier to maintain them even thank you
so much no worries thank you for having
me if you want to learn more about my
book creating software with modern
diagramming techniques on how you can
use it build a software is available
from all the main retailers available on
Amazon for free checking out thank you
I'll leave a link to Ashley's book in
The Links so you can learn more about
diagramming thank you so much for coming
Charlie for software engineering radio
thank you for listening
thanks for listening to SC radio an
educational program brought to you by
IEEE software magazine for more about
the podcast including other episodes
visit our website at sc-radio.net
to provide feedback you can comment on
each episode on the website or reach us
on LinkedIn Facebook Twitter or through
our slack Channel at SC radio dot
slack.com you can also email us at team
sc-radio.net
this and all other episodes of SC radio
is licensed under Creative Commons
license 2.5 thanks for listening
[Music]
foreign